Guide to the Margaret G. Reid Papers 1904-1990
University of Chicago Library
Reid, Margaret G. Papers
1904-1990
30.5 linear feet (54 boxes)
Hanna Holborn Gray Special Collections Research Center University of Chicago Library 1100 East 57th Street Chicago, Illinois 60637 U.S.A.
Margaret Gilpin Reid (1896-1991) was a Professor of Home Economics and Economics at the University of Chicago between 1951 and 1961. Reid was one of the first economists to theorize the economic contributions of non-market activities such as housework. Her work during the 1930s, which argued the household was a site of production as well as consumption, has been cited as an important forerunner to the "New Home Economics" of the 1960s. This collection contains Reid's research data and drafts of her books and papers. It also contains cards, clippings, professional and personal correspondence, and writings by other scholars. Material spans 1904-1990, concentrated in the 1930s through the early 1980s.
Information on Use
Access
The collection is open for research.
Biographical Note
Margaret Gilpin Reid (1896-1991) was an economist whose research interests centered on household production and consumption, and later on the relationships between health, income, and productivity. Her work on the importance of non-market activities such as housework is considered to have anticipated "New Home Economics" in the 1960s.
Reid was born in Canada and completed a degree in Home Economics at the University of Manitoba in 1921. She received her PhD from the University of Chicago in 1931. She taught briefly at Connecticut College, moving on to Iowa State College (Iowa State University) where she taught and researched until 1945. Her first book, Economics of Household Production, was published in 1934. Reid, like her PhD advisor Hazel Kyrk, sought to theorize the productive contribution made by domestic activities within the household. She drew much of her data from experimental agricultural stations in the Midwest. Her attention to labour skills and technologies applied in the home led her to conclude that the household was not only a site of consumption, but of production. Feminist economists would later argue that this work was underappreciated and even ignored, pointing out its similarity to Gary Becker's 1965 Nobel-prize winning theory of time allocation.
Reid served as an economic advisor to the Division of Statistical Standards during 1943 and 1944. She moved permanently to Washington the following year, where she served as the Head of Family Economics for the Department of Agriculture. She returned to academia in 1948, taking up a position in economics at the University of Chicago, Urbana-Champaign. She was also a member of the Association of Public and Land-grant Universities, reporting on price inflation and family budgets to its Committee on Postwar Agricultural Policy. Reid's tenure at Iowa State and at UIUC involved her in controversies about academic freedom: in Iowa, faculty chafed at the dairy lobby's control over the administration, while in Illinois a series of resignations protested the administration's removal of a popular Dean.
In 1951 Reid returned to the University of Chicago as a Professor of Home Economics and Economics. Although she became emeritus in 1961, she continued to research and write until her death in 1991. Her work at Chicago brought her in contact with economists such as Theodore W. Schultz (a colleague from Iowa) and Milton Friedman. She was an active member of Gary Becker's Applications of Economics Workshop. In later years her work was preoccupied with the relationship between demographic factors such as age, race, health, and income, and productivity and consumption.
The American Economic Association named Reid a Distinguished Fellow in 1980, recognizing her as a "truly tireless colleague" whose contributions to the field were complemented by a "felicitous sense of humour." In 1996 Feminist Economics devoted an issue to recognizing her research, and scholarship continues to try to restore her status as a pioneering economist.
Scope Note
This collection is divided into three series:
Series I: Research and Writings, contains Reid's research data and notes. "Data" refers both to raw data and calculations. The series includes correspondence, as well as articles, conference papers, and drafts of papers and books authored by Reid and other scholars. Of note is material related to her early research into household production and consumption, drawn from agricultural stations and farm agencies during the 1930s and 1940s. Oversized data has been transferred to Series III. Material spans the 1937 through 1986.
Subseries II: Personal, contains address books, bills, cards, certificates, clippings, personal correspondence, prints, a passport, and a journal. It also contains photographs of Reid's friends and family. Oversized certificates have been transferred to Series III. Material spans 1904-1990.
Subseries III: Oversize, contains clippings, certificates, and research data, transferred from Series I and II. It includes a copy of Reid's book Consumers and the Market. Newspaper clippings are in poor condition. Material spans 1938-1977.
Related Resources
The following related resources are located in the Department of Special Collections:
Browse finding aids by topic.
Subject Headings
Reid, Margaret G. (Margaret Gilpin), 1896-; Consumption (Economics); Home economics; Housing -- United States; Income -- United States
INVENTORY
- Series I: Research and Writings
  This series contains Reid's research data and notes. "Data" refers both to raw data and calculations. The series includes articles, conference papers, and drafts of papers and books. These were authored by Reid unless otherwise noted. Some folders contain related correspondence and one includes teaching materials. Oversize material has been moved to Series III. Material is divided into five subseries:
  Subseries 1: Household Economics, contains material related to Reid's early research and publication on household consumption and production. The bulk of the data and notes in this subseries were drawn from agricultural stations and collected by the Farm Security Administration (FSA) and Farmers' Home Administration (FAH); these loan agencies required farm families to keep detailed income and expenditure records during the 1930s and 1940s. These records are of particular note. Also of note are clippings and correspondence on the oleomargarine controversy at Iowa State College during 1943 and 1944, while Reid was faculty there. When faculty recommended wartime use of oleomargarine, the Iowa dairy lobby pressured the administration to change their publication. Some faculty resigned in protest. Material spans the 1930s-1979, primarily covering the period between 1937 and 1951. It is organized alphabetically by topic and title.
  Subseries 2: Income and Consumption, covers the middle part of Reid's career and documents her interest in the demographics of income and consumption, particularly in urban areas. This subseries contains data, research notes, and book drafts. It spans 1950-1978 and is organized alphabetically by topic and title.
  Subseries 3: Income and Health, contains data, notes, and drafts on the relationship between health, income, and productivity. These topics preoccupied Reid in the final stages of her career. Material spans 1964-1985, primarily covering the 1970s and early 1980s. It is organized alphabetically by topic and title.
  Subseries 4: General, contains computations, data, and research notes on unidentified topics. In also contains indexed bibliographies. It includes Reid's cv a list of her publications. Much of this material is undated, though it appears to cover the 1930s up to 1981.
  Subseries 5: Writings by Others, contains articles and papers written by other scholars. Reports by government departments or other institutions are filed by topic along with other research material in the preceding subseries. These writings are organized by author and span the 1930s-1986.
  - Subseries 1: Household Economics
    - "Adjustments of Rural Families to Economic Change, University of Tennessee, 1945 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - "Changing Composition of Family Budgets for Selected Groups of Corn Belt Farmers," Department of Agriculture, 1940-1942 (Box 1, Folder 2-3)
    - Current Population Survey (CPS), data, 1948, 1950 (Box 1, Folder 4-6)
    - CPS, re-tabulation of data, undated (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - Data, 1940s (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - Economic behavior and value, notes, 1936 (Box 1, Folder 9)
    - "The Economic Contribution of Homemakers," 1947-1948 (Box 1, Folder 10-11)
    - Economics and sociology, notes, undated (Box 1, Folder 12)
    - "Elasticity of Expenditure in Relation to Income for Families of Different Economic Levels," draft and data, 1940s (Box 1, Folder 13)
    - "Family Economics Tri-annual Report," 1950 (Box 1, Folder 14)
    - Family expenditures, draft and correspondence, 1951 (Box 1, Folder 14)
    - Family size, data and notes, 1941-1944 (Box 1, Folder 16)
    - Farm budget data, Iowa State College, 1940s (Box 2, Folder 1)
    - Farm family budgets, 1941-1942 (Box 2, Folder 2)
    - Farm family expenditures, data and notes, 1939-1940, undated (Box 2, Folder 3-7)
    - Farm family incomes, data and notes, 1949, undated (Box 2, Folder 8-9)
    - "Farm Family Living," conference paper, 1946 (Box 2, Folder 10)
    - Farm Family Living in Illinois, study, 1946 (Box 3, Folder 1)
    - "Farm Family Living Prospects in 1946," 1945 (Box 3, Folder 2)
    - Farm and home account books, blank, undated (Box 3, Folder 3-7)
    - Farm and home accounts, computations, undated (Box 3, Folder 8)
    - Farm and home accounts, notes, 1946 (Box 3, Folder 9)
    - Farm and home accounts by state, data, 1940-1942 (Box 3, Folder 10)
    - Farm Security Administration (FSA), data, 1940s (Box 4, Folder 1-6)
    - FSA, Illinois Office, data, 1946 (Box 4, Folder 7)
    - Farmers' Home Administration (FHA), Annual Income Reports, 1950-1951 (Box 4, Folder 8-9)
    - FHA, loan data, 1940s (Box 4, Folder 10-13)
    - "Farmers in a Changing World: The 1940 Yearbook of Agriculture," with D.D. Hammerburg and L.J. Norton, 1941 (Box 4, Folder 14)
    - Food consumption, farm families in southern counties, data, 1947-1948 (Box 5, Folder 1)
    - "Food Consumption of Low Income Families," statement before the Joint Committee on Economic Report, 1950 (Box 5, Folder 2)
    - Food expenditures, rural and urban families, data, 1940s (Box 5, Folder 3-6)
    - Household economics, notes, undated (Box 5, Folder 7)
    - Household expenditures, data and correspondence, 1953 (Box 6, Folder 1)
    - Household income, notes, undated (Box 6, Folder 2-3)
    - "The Household as Producer," conference paper and correspondence, 1979 (Box 6, Folder 4-5)
    - Household time and cost, bibliographies, 1930s-1940s (Box 6, Folder 6-7)
    - Housing, data, 1968 (Box 7, Folder 1)
    - "Housing and Income," draft, 1961 (Box 7, Folder 2-5)
    - "Human Resources and Community," Iowa State University report, 1975 (Box 7, Folder 6)
    - Hurwitz, notes, 1945 (Box 7, Folder 7)
    - Illinois, data, 1937-1941 (Box 7, Folder 8)
    - "Income Expenditure Patterns of Farm Operator Families," draft and notes, undated (Box 8, Folder 1-2)
    - Intercity Correlations of Food With Respect to Income," draft, 1964 (Box 8, Folder 3)
    - Iowa, data, 1943-1949 (Box 8, Folder 4-6)
    - Iowa Farm Account Book, blank, undated (Box 8, Folder 7)
    - Iowa Farm Family Budget Records, 1940-1942 (Box 8, Folder 8)
    - Iowa home accounts, data, 1939-1941 (Box 8, Folder 9)
    - "Iowa Incomes," with Virginia Britton, 1938 (Box 8, Folder 10)
    - Iowa State College and the oleomargarine controversy, clippings and correspondence, 1943-1944 (Box 9, Folder 1-2)
    - Iowa State College, memoranda, 1941-1943 (Box 9, Folder 3)
    - "Is the Inflation Danger Passed?" radio roundtable with J. Kenneth Galbraith, A.G. Hart, and Maynard Krueger, 1944 (Box 9, Folder 4)
    - John Wiley and Sons Publishers, correspondence, 1979 (Box 9, Folder 5)
    - Kansas, data, 1940s (Box 9, Folder 6-7)
    - Kansas, farm surveys, blank, 1948-1949 (Box 9, Folder 8)
    - Kansas and North Carolina, data, 1930s (Box 9, Folder 9)
    - "Major Categories of Farm Consumption," data and notes, 1949 (Box 9, Folder 10)
    - Marital status, data, 1960 (Box 9, Folder 11)
    - "Measures of Food and Associated Conditions," draft, 1966 (Box 9, Folder 12)
    - Mississippi, farm study, correspondence and data, 1949 (Box 9, Folder 13)
    - "Nutritional Aspects and Farm Family Needs in a Food and Nutrition Policy," 1947 (Box 10, Folder 1)
    - "Obstacles to Better Nutrition," 1945 (Box 10, Folder 2)
    - "The Outlook for Family Living," conference paper, 1945 (Box 10, Folder 3)
    - Population statistics, 1940s (Box 10, Folder 4)
    - "Postwar Agricultural Policy: Report on the Committee of the Association of Land-grant Colleges and Universities," 1944 (Box 10, Folder 5)
    - "Psychological Analysis of Economic Behaviour," Katona, book review, 1951 (Box 10, Folder 6)
    - "Reconsideration of the Physiological Energy Value of Foods," Department of Agriculture, 1947 (Box 10, Folder 7)
    - "Relation of the Within Group Transitory Component of Incomes to the Income Elasticity of Family Expenditures, draft, undated (Box 10, Folder 8-9)
    - "Research in the Bureau of Human Nutrition and Home Economics," 1951 (Box 10, Folder 10)
    - "Survey of Food Consumption by Open Country Families," Department of Agriculture, 1945 (Box 10, Folder 11)
    - "Trends in Work of Married Women," 1943 (Box 10, Folder 12-13)
    - University of Illinois controversy, Everett E. Hagen, letter of resignation, 1951 (Box 10, Folder 14)
    - "Wartime Farm and Food Policy: Food Strategy," 1943 (Box 10, Folder 15)
  - Subseries 2: Income and Consumption
    - Adjusted Food Expenditure, data, 1950-1960 (Box 10, Folder 16)
    - Age, income, and male population by city, data, data, 1950-1972 (Box 10, Folder 17)
    - "Coefficients of Elasticity of Food," draft, 1960 (Box 11, Folder 1)
    - "Comments on Research in Human Capital," conference paper, 1975 (Box 11, Folder 2)
    - "Components of Income of Consumer Units by Urbanization and Region," draft, undated (Box 11, Folder 3)
    - Consumer sovereignty, discussion, undated (Box 11, Folder 4)
    - "Consumers and the Market," course materials and student work, 1955-1956 (Box 11, Folder 5)
    - Consumption, articles, 1960s (Box 11, Folder 6)
    - Consumption in cities, data, 1977 (Box 11, Folder 7)
    - Consumption economics, notes, undated (Box 11, Folder 8)
    - "Consumption of Families in Metro Areas," draft and data, circa 1972 (Box 11, Folder 9)
    - "Consumption Levels of the American People," draft, undated (Box 11, Folder 10)
    - "Consumption Patterns and Trends," conference paper, 1964 (Box 11, Folder 11)
    - Educational Attainment, 1970 Census, 1970 (Box 11, Folder 12)
    - "The Evolution of U.S. Agriculture," World Food Forum, paper and proceedings, 1972 (Box 11, Folder 13-14)
    - "Expenditure-income Curves of Food," draft, 1969 (Box 12, Folder 1)
    - "Expenditures for Furniture and Equipment," draft, undated (Box 12, Folder 2)
    - "Food Expenditures of Urban Consumer Units," drafts, 1968 (Box 12, Folder 3-7)
    - Food and income," draft, 1962 (Box 13, Folder 1-2)
    - "Food, Income, and Expenditure," draft, undated (Box 13, Folder 3)
    - "Food, Income, and Prices of Areas in the U.S.," draft, 1971 (Box 13, Folder 4-6)
    - "Food With Respect to Income of Consumers," draft, 1964 (Box 13, Folder 7)
    - "How Much Poverty and its Relation to H.R. 10440," draft, undated (Box 13, Folder 8)
    - Income, bibliography, undated (Box 13, Folder 9)
    - Income, data, 1942-1970 (Box 13, Folder 10)
    - Income, data, 1970s (Box 14, Folder 1-2)
    - "Income Components and Consumption," draft, undated (Box 14, Folder 2-4)
    - Income and consumption, data and notes, 1960-1965 (Box 14, Folder 5-6)
    - Income and consumption, data and notes, 1970-1971, undated (Box 15, Folder 1-6)
    - Income and consumption, draft and data, 1978 (Box 15, Folder 7)
    - Income and consumption, draft, undated (Box 16, Folder 1-2)
    - income and consumption, excerpt, undated (Box 16, Folder 3)
    - Income and consumption, metro areas, data, 1960 (Box 16, Folder 4)
    - Income and consumption, urban and rural areas, data, undated (Box 16, Folder 5)
    - Income elasticity, computation, 1978 (Box 16, Folder 6-7)
    - Income inequality, data and notes, 1971 (Box 17, Folder 1)
    - "Income and Levels of Consumption," draft, 1952 (Box 17, Folder 2)
    - Income and Medicare, data, 1972 (Box 17, Folder 3)
    - Income, savings, and consumption, discussion, undated (Box 17, Folder 4)
    - "Income and Welfare in the U.S.," book review, 1963 (Box 17, Folder 5)
    - "Increasing the Efficiency of Consumer Buymanship," 1963 (Box 17, Folder 6)
    - "Inequality of Average Income of Urban Units," draft, 1976 (Box 17, Folder 7)
    - "Inequality in Income Distribution," discussion, undated (Box 17, Folder 8)
    - "Inequality of Income Distribution," draft, undated (Box 17, Folder 9)
    - Metro areas, footnote draft, 1976 (Box 17, Folder 10)
    - Migration, data, 1978 (Box 17, Folder 11-12)
    - Price indexes of cities, data, undated (Box 18, Folder 1)
    - "Structure of Expenditure and Income," drafts, 1968 (Box 18, Folder 2-5)
    - "Structure of Expenditure and Income, undated (Box 18, Folder 6)
    - "Structure of Expenditure and Income, undated (Box 19, Folder 1-3)
    - "Structure of Income and Consumption, Vol. I," drafts, 1967 (Box 19, Folder 4-7)
    - "Structure of Income and Consumption, Vol. I," drafts, 1967 (Box 20, Folder 1-8)
    - "Structure of Income and Consumption, Vol. I," drafts, 1967 (Box 21, Folder 1-5)
    - "Structure of Income and Consumption, Vol. I," drafts, 1967 (Box 22, Folder 1-6)
    - "Structure of Income and Consumption, Ch. 7," draft, 1968 (Box 22, Folder 7)
    - "Structure of Income and Consumption, Vol. I," draft, 1969 (Box 22, Folder 8)
    - "Structure of Income and Consumption, Vol. I," draft, 1969 (Box 23, Folder 1-6)
    - "Structure of Income and Consumption, Vol. II," draft outline, 1969 (Box 23, Folder 7)
    - "Structure of Income and Consumption, Vol. I.," draft, 1970 (Box 23, Folder 8-10)
    - "Structure of Income and Consumption, Vol. I.," draft, 1970 (Box 24, Folder 1-4)
    - "Structure of Income and Consumption, Vol. II," draft, 1970 (Box 24, Folder 5-6)
    - "Structure of Income and Consumption, Vol. II," draft, 1970 (Box 25, Folder 1-9)
    - "Structure of Income and Consumption," draft, 1971 (Box 25, Folder 10)
    - "Structure of Income and Consumption," draft and correspondence, 1971 (Box 26, Folder 1-4)
    - "Structure of Income and Consumption," drafts, undated (Box 26, Folder 5-7)
    - "Structure of Income and Consumption," drafts, undated (Box 27, Folder 1-5)
    - "Structure of Income and Consumption," drafts, undated (Box 28, Folder 1)
    - Structure of income and consumption, urban consumers, data, circa 1967 (Box 28, Folder 2-3)
    - Structure of income and consumption, urban consumers, draft, undated (Box 28, Folder 4-7)
    - "Theories of Consumption and Income Distribution," drafts with review comments, 1971 (Box 29, Folder 1-4)
    - Trends in Social and Economic Conditions in Metropolitan and Non-metropolitan Areas," Bureau of the Census, 1970 (Box 29, Folder 5)
    - Urban consumer units by age of head and income, notes and data, undated (Box 29, Folder 6)
    - Veterans, income, data, 1960-1970 (Box 29, Folder 7)
  - Subseries 3: Income and Health
    - "Age Distribution and Death Rates of Populations: Males by Colour," draft, undated (Box 29, Folder 8)
    - "Age Distributions and Health of Populations" drafts and data, 1981-1983, undated (Box 30, Folder 1-3)
    - Age, health, and labour, notes, circa 1970s-1980s (Box 30, Folder 4)
    - "Average Characteristics of Males of Disability Surveys," draft and data, circa 1970s-1980s (Box 30, Folder 5)
    - California Public Health Statistical Report," 1964 (Box 30, Folder 6)
    - "Changes in Medical Care Prices of Cities," drafts and data, circa 1960s (Box 30, Folder 7-8)
    - "Characteristics of Economic Resources of Males of Metro Areas and States," draft, 1973 (Box 30, Folder 9)
    - Computations, 1983 (Box 31, Folder 1)
    - Data, 1983 (Box 31, Folder 2-3)
    - Data by state, 1978-1983 (Box 31, Folder 4-5)
    - Death rates, data, 1977-1984 (Box 31, Folder 6-9)
    - Death rates, data, undated (Box 32, Folder 1-4)
    - Death rates, age, data, 1975 (Box 32, Folder 5)
    - Death rates, age and race, drafts and data, 1972, 1977 (Box 32, Folder 6-7)
    - Death rates, males, data, undated (Box 32, Folder 8)
    - Death rates, males by state, data, undated (Box 32, Folder 9)
    - Death rates, other variables, data, undated (Box 32, Folder 10)
    - Death rates, statistics and correspondence, 1976 (Box 32, Folder 11)
    - Death rates, white males, data and notes, undated (Box 32, Folder 12-14)
    - Death rates, white males, age adjustments, data, circa 1970s (Box 32, Folder 15)
    - Death rates, years, data, 1987 (Box 32, Folder 16)
    - "Death Rates and Demographic Characteristics of Populations," drafts and notes, 1971, undated (Box 33, Folder 1-2)
    - "Death Rates and Economic Factors," drafts, 1973, 1978 (Box 33, Folder 3-5)
    - Death rates and income, drafts and data, 1976 (Box 33, Folder 6-7)
    - "Death Rates of Persons by Annual Income and Schooling," drafts and data, 1980 (Box 34, Folder 1)
    - Death rates of populations, data and notes, 1982-1983 (Box 34, Folder 2-5)
    - "Death Rates of Populations by Age, Sex, and Colour," drafts, 1978 (Box 34, Folder 6-9)
    - "Death Rates of Populations by Age, Sex, and Colour," drafts, 1978 (Box 35, Folder 1)
    - "Death Rates of Populations of Areas and their Demographic Characteristics," draft, 1973 (Box 35, Folder 2)
    - Death rates of state populations, drafts and data, 1976 (Box 35, Folder 3-4)
    - "Death Rates of State Populations by Race, Age, and Economic Factors," draft, undated (Box 35, Folder 5)
    - Disability and labour, data, circa 1970s (Box 35, Folder 6)
    - "Disability of Household Populations of Income Groups," draft, 1980 (Box 35, Folder 7-8)
    - Disability surveys, circa 1970s (Box 35, Folder 9)
    - "Economic Resources and Health," drafts and data, 1978 (Box 36, Folder 1-4)
    - Education and health, draft, circa 1980 (Box 36, Folder 5)
    - "An Exploration of Conflicting Evidence of Death Rates and Income," drafts, 1976 (Box 36, Folder 6-9)
    - "An Exploration of Conflicting Evidence of Death Rates and Income," drafts, 1976 (Box 37, Folder 1)
    - "An Exploration of Conflicting Evidence of Death Rates and Income," reviews and correspondence, 1976-1977 (Box 37, Folder 2)
    - Health, data and notes, 1980s, undated (Box 37, Folder 3-7)
    - Health, footnote drafts, circa 1980s (Box 37, Folder 8)
    - Health, age, and income, data, 1980s (Box 37, Folder 9)
    - "Health, Age, and Income of Populations," drafts, 1983, 1985 (Box 37, Folder 10-11)
    - "Health, Age, and Income of Populations," drafts, 1983, 1985 (Box 38, Folder 1-7)
    - Health, age, and race, data, circa 1980s (Box 38, Folder 8-11)
    - Health conclusions, draft, 1982 (Box 38, Folder 12)
    - "Health and Economic Resources," draft, 1976 (Box 38, Folder 13)
    - Health and income, data and notes, undated (Box 38, Folder 14-15)
    - "Health of Members of Populations of Households," draft, undated (Box 38, Folder 16)
    - Health by state, data, undated (Box 39, Folder 1)
    - "Health Status and Income," drafts, 1980, 1982 (Box 39, Folder 2-4)
    - Health variables, draft and data, undated (Box 39, Folder 5)